Rufus Columbus Burleson papers, Inclusive: 1836-1966, undated, Bulk: 1891-1897
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Rufus Columbus Burleson papers
Inclusive: 1836-1966, undated, Bulk: 1891-1897
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
57
Burleson, Rufus Columbus, 1823 - 1901
9 document boxes.
The Rufus Columbus Burleson papers contains manuscripts of Reverend Burleson, former president of Baylor University. This collection consists primarily of personal correspondence and literary productions such as sermons, students’ essays, newspaper clippings, class rosters, and notes. Financial papers, legal documents, and a family photo album are also included.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Rufus Columbus Burleson was born in Decatur, Alabama, on 1823 August 7, to Jonathon Burleson and Elizabeth Byrd. He was one of thirteen children (8 daughters and 5 sons). From his early years, Burleson was an excellent student who strove to distinguish himself from among his peers. Throughout his youth, he had strong aspirations to attend law school. At the age of sixteen, Burleson had a conversion experience at a Baptist revival and chose to devote his life to the ministry instead. He enrolled in Western Baptist Theological Seminary in Covington, Kentucky and graduated with his degree in 1846.
In 1848, Burleson moved to the Texas frontier as a Baptist missionary a few years after the state had been annexed to the United States. He had been called upon to replace William Tryon, the recently deceased pastor of the First Baptist Church in Houston.
Throughout their ventures in Texas, Rufus C. Burleson and his brother Richard B. Burleson were among the most influential Baptists in the state. A strong moral education was seen as vital to the sanctity of the Baptist denomination both in the training of future ministers and the molding of virtuous citizens. This dream became realized upon the establishment of Baylor University on 1845 February 1. Although Rufus was not in Texas at this time, he quickly became involved in raising funds and publicity for the fledgling university.
Rufus Burleson’s rising popularity and influence brought about significant changes in his life. In 1851, Burleson ascended to the presidency of Baylor University in Independence, Texas. Under his leadership, Baylor University grew into a formidable institution. On 1853 January 3, he married Georgia Jenkins. On November 19 of the following year, Burleson baptized famous Independence resident General Sam Houston.
Despite his great successes as Baylor’s president, Burleson’s term of office was increasingly filled with problems. Raising money to keep Baylor’s doors open was always difficult, and Burleson did not always agree with Horace Clark, the principal of Baylor’s Female Department, on many university issues. Burleson left Baylor in 1861 to take charge of Waco University.
Despite the long tenure of William Crane as the next president of Baylor, and his attempts to raise funds, the university was unable to sustain itself financially. In 1886, Burleson became the first president of Baylor University after Baylor moved from Independence to Waco and merged with Waco University. Burleson served in this administrative capacity until 1897. During this time, Burleson’s reputation was marred by controversy. In 1894, a young Brazilian girl living with the Burleson family became pregnant. Although a jury found Burleson innocent of the accusations brought against him, his reputation never recovered.
Even after resigning from his position as president, Burleson continued to work for the interests of the University over the next four years. Burleson passed away in Waco, Texas on 1901 May 14 at the age of 77.
Scope and Content
The Rufus Columbus Burleson papers includes business and personal correspondence, legal documents, financial records, a family photo album, newspaper clippings, books, diaries, ledgers, class rosters, sermons, advertisements, and students’ essays. Correspondence comprises the bulk of the collection, highlighting Rufus Burleson’s life journey, particularly his terms as president of Baylor University.
Much of the original classification for the collection has been maintained. Folders containing empty envelopes were removed and unique stamps and letterheads are currently being processed. The most significant change occurred in dealing with the correspondence series. Although the letters were already arranged chronologically, frequent correspondents to Rufus Burleson were separated from the general subseries. Examples include former Baylor President William Carey Crane and Burleson’s brother Richard Burleson.
Arrangement
The Rufus Columbus Burleson papers is arranged in 5 series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal Documents, III. Financial Documents, IV. Literary Productions, V. Photographic Material. Appendix A includes a quick overview of Rufus Burleson’s immediate family.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 57.
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Georgia Jenkins Burleson collection, Inclusive: circa 1850-1934, undated, Bulk: circa 1850- circa 1870
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Burleson, Georgia Jenkins, 1833-1924.; Burleson, Rufus Columbus, 1823-1901.; Crane, William Carey, 1816-1885.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University (Independence, Tex.) -- History.; Baylor University -- Presidents.
Subjects
Baptists -- Sermons.; Financial records.; Legal documents.; Notes (documents); Photographs.
Genres
Correspondence.
- Correspondence, 1843-1966, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series of correspondence comprises most of the collection. The majority of the letters are personal exchanges between Rufus C. Burleson and family members, fellow ministers, Baylor officials, Baylor students, and organizations such as the Texas Baptist Herald.
  - General, 1843-1856 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1858-1859 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1860-1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, 1864-1871 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 1872-1879 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General, 1880-1886 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General, 1887-1890 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 1891 February-June 7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General, 1891 June 12-July (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General, 1891 August 8-27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General, 1891 August 28-September 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General, 1891 September 3-5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General, 1891 September 6-12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General, 1891 September 14-25 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General, 1891 September 26- November (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General, 1891 December-1892 January (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - General, 1892 February-April (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General, 1892 May-August (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General, 1892 September-October (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - General, 1892 November-December 12 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - General, 1892 December 13-31 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - General, 1893 January 1-12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General, 1893 January 13-31 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - General, 1893 February 1-13 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - General, 1893 February 14-17 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - General, 1893 February 18-27 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - General, 1893 March 1-8 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - General, 1893 March 10-17 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - General, 1893 March 18-25 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - General, 1893 March 26-April 8 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - General, 1893 April 11-22 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General, 1893 April 23-29 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General, 1893 May 1-8 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General, 1893 May 9-20 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General, 1893 May 21-29 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General, 1893 June (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General, 1893 July-August (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General, 1893 September (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General, 1893 October (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General, 1893 November (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General, 1893 December 1-14 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General, 1893 December 16-26 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General, 1894 January 1-26 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General, 1894 February 2-28 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - General, 1894 March-April 16 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - General, 1894 April 18-June (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - General, 1894 August-October 10 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - General, 1894 October 29-December (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - General, 1894 January 5-18 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - General, 1895 January 19-30 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - General, 1895 February 2-19 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - General, 1895 February 20-26 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - General, 1895 March 1-5 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - General, 1895 March 6-13 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - General, 1895 March 14-25 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - General, 1895 March 26-31 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - General, 1895 April 1-7 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - General, 1895 April 9-17 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - General, 1895 April 18-25 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - General, 1895 April 26-May 5 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - General, 1895 May 8-12 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - General, 1895 May 13-24 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: General, 1895 May 25-June (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - General, 1895 July-August (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - General, 1895 September 2-14 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General, 1895 September 17-25 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General, 1895 September 26-October 20 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General, 1895 October 25-31 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General, 1895 November 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: General, 1895 November 16-20 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General, 1895 November 21-30 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General, 1895 December 2-17 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General, 1895 December 20-31 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - General, 1896 January 1-5 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - General, 1896 January 6-15 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - General, 1896 January 16-20 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - General, 1896 January 22-29 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - General, 1896 January 30- February 9 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - General, 1896 February 10-17 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - General, 1896 February 19-26 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - General, 1896 February 27-March 5 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - General, 1896 March 7-11 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - General, 1896 March 12-17 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - General, 1896 March 18-27 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - General, 1896 March 28-April 9 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - General, 1896 April 10-15 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - General, 1896 April 16-26 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - General, 1896 April 27-30 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - General, 1896 May 1-12 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - General, 1896 May 13-28 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - General, 1896 June 1-25 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - General, 1896 June 27-July (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - General, 1896 August 1-21 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - General, 1896 August 22-September 5 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - General, 1896 September 7-12 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - General, 1896 September 14-24 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - General, 1896 September 25- October 5 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General, 1896 October 6-23 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General, 1896 October 23-31 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - General, 1896 November 1-8 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - General, 1896 November 9-15 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - General, 1896 November 16-21 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - General, 1896 November 23-30 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - General, 1896 December 1-8 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - General, 1896 December 9-16 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - General, 1896 December 17-21 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - General, 1896 December 23-28 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - General, 1896 December 29-31 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - General, 1897 January 1-12 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - General, 1897 January 13-31 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - General, 1897 February 1-12 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - General, 1897 February 13-15 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - General, 1897 February 16-28 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - General, 1897 March 1-7 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - General, 1897 March 9-13 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - General, 1897 March 15-20 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - General, 1897 March 22-27 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - General, 1897 March 28-31 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - General, 1897 April 1-6 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - General, 1897 April 7-9 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - General, 1897 April 10-13 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - General, 1897 April 14-24 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - General, 1897 April 25-28 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - General, 1897 April 29-May 3 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - General, 1897 May 4-17 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - General, 1897 May 18-28 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - General, 1897 May 31-November (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - General, 1898 January-April (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - General, 1898 May-1899 April (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General, 1899 May-December (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - General, 1900-1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General: Folder 1 of 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - General: Folder 2 of 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - General: Folder 3 of 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - General: Folder 4 of 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - General: Folder 5 of 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - General: Folder 6 of 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - General: Folder 7 of 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - General: Folder 8 of 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - General: Folder 9 of 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - General: Folder 10 of 10, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - David Abner, Jr. to Rufus C. Burleson, 1893-1896 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - George W. Baines to/from Rufus C. Burleson, 1860-1897 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - R.E.B. Baylor from Rufus C. Burleson, 1854 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Baylor University, 1859-1896 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - A.A. Burleson to Rufus C. Burleson, 1892-1897 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Dabny Burleson to/from Rufus C. Burleson, 1868-1896 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Rufus C. Burleson to Texas Baptist Herald, 1860 July-1872 May 8 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Rufus C. Burleson to Texas Baptist Herald, 1872 May 15-1873 March (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Richard Burleson to Texas Baptist Herald, 1873-1874 April (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Georgia Jenkins Burleson, 1849-1895 undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Richard Burleson to/from Rufus C. Burleson, 1847-September 1856 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Richard Burleson to/from Rufus C. Burleson, 1856 October-1861 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Rufus C. Burleson to Texas Baptist Herald, 1856-1858 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Rufus C. Burleson to Texas Baptist Herald, 1859-June 1860 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Rufus C. Burleson to Texas Baptist Herald, 1875 February-April 8 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Rufus C. Burleson to Texas Baptist Herald, 1875 April 8-May (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Rufus C. Burleson to Texas Baptist Herald, 1875 July-1877 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - B.H. Carroll, 1875-1897, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - F.H. Claypool to Rufus C. Burleson, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - W. Carey Crane from Rufus C. Burleson, 1845-1849 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - W. Carey Crane from Rufus C. Burleson, 1860-1868 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - W. Carey Crane from Rufus C. Burleson, 1869-1870 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - W. Carey Crane from Rufus C. Burleson, 1871-1873 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - W. Carey Crane from Rufus C. Burleson, 1874-1875 April (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - W. Carey Crane from Rufus C. Burleson, 1875 May-August (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - W. Carey Crane from Rufus C. Burleson, 1878 January-August 9 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - W. Carey Crane from Rufus C. Burleson, 1878 August 20-November (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - W. Carey Crane from Rufus C. Burleson, 1879 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - W. Carey Crane from Rufus C. Burleson, 1881-1882 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - L.A. Downing to Rufus C. Burleson, 1891-1892 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - M.D. Early to Rufus C. Burleson, 1893-1896 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - John F. Elder to Rufus C. Burleson, 1893-1897 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Family to Rufus C. Burleson, 1883-1895 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Family to Rufus C. Burleson, 1896-1899, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Corra Bacon Foster to Rufus C. Burleson, 1893-1896 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - B.F. Fuller to Rufus C. Burleson, 1896-1897 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - J.B. Gambrell to Rufus C. Burleson, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Elder H. Garrett to/from Rufus C. Burleson, 1860-1861 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - P. Hams to Rufus C. Burleson, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - S.A. Hayden to Rufus C. Burleson, 1891-1896 October (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - S.A. Hayden to Rufus C. Burleson, 1896 November-1897 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - A.J. Holt to Rufus C. Burleson, 1893-1897 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Invitations, 1885-1918, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Henry A. Ivy to/from Rufus C. Burleson, 1895-1897 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - A.M. Johnson to Rufus C. Burleson, 1890-1895 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - B.F. Johnson to Rufus C. Burleson, 1895-1897 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Eustace E. King to Rufus C. Burleson, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - W.H. Kuykendall to Rufus C. Burleson, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - W.H. Long, Sr. to Rufus C. Burleson, 1891-1897 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - L.R. Millican to Rufus C. Burleson, 1891-1897 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Elle Orecoll to Rufus C. Burleson, 1897 April (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - S.H. Slaughter to Rufus C. Burleson, 1895-1897 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Willis Upshaw to Rufus C. Burleson, 1896-1897, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - John Ward to/from Rufus C. Burleson, 1891-1896 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - J.M. Welborne to Rufus C. Burleson, 1896 January-April 4 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - J.M. Welborne to Rufus C. Burleson, 1896 April 6-June (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Legal Documents, 1836-1857, undated; 2
  This short series includes portions of wills, records of court proceedings, and affidavits.
  - Legal Documents: Burleson Family: General, 1836-1857, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
- Financial Documents, 1850-1947; 3
  This short series contains papers for Burleson’s personal finances as well as those of Baylor University.
  - Financial Documents: Baylor University: General, 1850-1867 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Financial Documents: Baylor University: General, 1870-1947 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Financial Documents: Rufus C. Burleson: General, 1873-1893 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Financial Documents: Rufus C. Burleson: General, 1894-1899 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Literary Productions, 1840-1958, undated; 4
  This large literary series includes a vast array of documents including pamphlets, published sermons, newspaper clippings, class rosters, students’ assignments, and various books. Burleson’s affiliation with Baylor is quite evident in this series.
  - Biographical: Sketches, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Minutes: Texas House of Representatives, 1893 February 18 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets: Rufus C. Burleson: “Family Government”, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Speeches: Rufus C. Burleson: Memorial for Sam Houston, 1893 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Sermons: Rufus C. Burleson: General, 1846-1849, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Sermons: Rufus C. Burleson: Dedication of Huntsville Baptist Church, 1891 July (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Sermons: Rufus C. Burleson: Memorial for Rev. Dr. James Stribling, 1892 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Sermons: Notes: Rufus C. Burleson, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Sermons: Brother Sanders, 1841-1842 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Clippings: General, 1856-1908 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Clippings: General, 1943-1958, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Clippings: Rufus C. Burleson, 1865-1901 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Programs: General, 1892-1900, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Business Cards: General, 1895-1918, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Baylor University: Prospective Teachers, 1890-1900, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Rosters: Baylor University Students, 1869-1891 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Sheet Music: Dixie: A Souvenir of the Confederacy, 1859 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Essays: Baylor University Students: English Bishops’ Trial (1 of 3), undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Essays: Baylor University Students: English Bishops’ Trial (2 of 3), undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Essays: Baylor University Students: English Bishops’ Trial (3 of 3), undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Essays: Baylor University Students: Conscience (1 of 2), undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Essays: Baylor University Students: Conscience (2 of 2), undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Essays: Student Quizzes: Texas History, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Notes: Rufus C. Burleson: Hebrew Grammar, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Notes: General (1 of 2), undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Notes: General (2 of 2), undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Manuscripts: Lectures: Rufus C. Burleson, 1875, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Manuscripts: Religious Reports, 1840-1861, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Manuscripts: Texas Education System, 1875-1880 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Manuscripts: Texas Education System, 1880-1897 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts: Texas Education System, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Printed Materials: The Guardian, 1891-1892, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Printed Materials: Blank Applications, 1890, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Printed Materials: Booklets: Texas Baptists, 1859-1888 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Printed Materials: Advertisements: General, 1892-1897 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Printed Materials: Advertisements: General (1 of 2), undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Printed Materials: Advertisements: General (2 of 2), undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Printed Materials: Advertisements: Book Catalogs, 1893-1895 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Printed Materials: Advertisements: Educational, 1893-1898, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Printed Materials: Advertisements: Baylor University, 1869-1891 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Printed Materials: Advertisements: Religious, 1865-1895, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Book: Tuition Ledger, 1866-1870 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Book: Grade book, 1871 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Book: Diary: Rufus C. Burleson, 1847-1849 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Book: School Records, 1876-1877 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Book: A Brief History of the Burleson Family, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Book: Register of Book Prices, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Book: School Register, 1842 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Book: Ledger: Hallie Byrd Burleson, 1878 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Book: Roster of Former Students, 1883 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Tribute: Dr. Rufus Columbus Burleson, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Photographic Materials, 1696-1881; 5
  This series includes a complete photo album of the Burleson family.
  - Photographic Materials: Photo Album: Burleson Family, 1869-1881, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)